# Dr. Avinash Kumar Singh

Hyderabad, India | +91-9005722861 | avinashkumarsingh1986@gmail.com | http://avinashkumarsingh.in

### **Profile**

With over 12 years in AI, I have navigated roles as an ML Researcher, Engineer, and Product Manager. I have deployed deep learning-based computer vision and NLP models on robots like Nao and Pepper, boards like Jetson Nano, Raspberry Pi, and NXP. My work spans to build and deploy AI models over edge devices, IOT and cloud platforms such as AWS, GCP, and E2E, addressing concurrency, security, and latency. On one hand my academic background, including a Ph.D. and postdocs, deepens my understanding of neural networks across diverse data types while the industrial exposure helped me to deploy the models in production and serving the real users. This blend of research and industry experience enables me to craft and deliver effective AI solutions.

## **Experience**

### DIRECTOR AI | BRANE ENTERPRISES LLP, HYDERABAD, INDIA | MAY 2020 - PRESENT

- Implemented a Face Recognition-based office attendance system, replacing the existing RFID system, and achieving organization-wide deployment.
- The system serves 2,856 employees with a 97.63% accuracy rate, resulting in annual savings in operational costs.
- Led a groundbreaking project to design smart glasses for visually impaired individuals, providing comprehensive assistance in reading, navigation, currency identification, person recognition, and scene understanding.
- The system can detect obstacle up to 5 feet, can help in reading English and six Indian languages, could recognize 9,605 objects and labels with 89.76% accuracy.
- Successfully delivered a Driver Monitoring System (DMS), incorporating real-time monitoring and safety features. The system tracks driver drowsiness, smoking, drinking, eating, phone usage, and seatbelt compliance, resulting in a 40% reduction in driving violations.
- Captured and recorded over 1,000 violations with images, date, time, and other details.
- Provided live streams from both interior and exterior dash cameras, enhancing monitoring accuracy.

### SENIOR RESEARCHER | MONTPELLIER UNIVERSITY, FRANCE | NOV 2020- NOV 2021

- I was associated with the robotics lab (LIRMM) and worked on the EU Project <u>SOPHIA</u>. As the in-charge of Work package 5, I helped my team to coordinate between different project partners <u>Italian Institute of Technology</u>, <u>Italy</u>, <u>INAIL</u>, <u>Italy</u>, and <u>LIRMM</u>, <u>France</u> for data acquisition, human-robot interaction and to derive a deep learning model for action recognition.
- Designed and developed a sensor agnostic, Bidirectional LSTM based deep neural network for action recognition.
   The model is tested in the presence of <u>Xsens suit</u> (used for motion capture) and Intel RealSense and Microsoft Kinect RGB-D data (3D skeleton). The research is published in <u>21st International Conference on Humanoid Robots</u>.
- The model is integrated with KUKA robot to help human in physical assistance, e.g. carrying object, release object, place object etc. in industrial environment by understanding the human actions.

### POST DOCTORAL RESEARCHER | UMEA UNIVERSITY, SWEDEN | FEB 2018 - JAN 2020

- During this postdoc, I closely worked with Professor <u>Kai-Florian Richter</u> and <u>Professor Thomas Hellström</u>. I was a part of intelligent robotics lab, during this postdoc, we designed a dialogue based human robot interaction system that allows humans, to talk to the robot. This work was published in a 'A' rated conference <u>ECAI-2020</u>.
- We developed and implemented a robot collaboration framework that enables robots to have dialogues by translating their actions into the natural language. This work was published in <u>Journal of behavioural robotics</u> and also featured in Softbank robotics under the <u>best 20 projects in 2020</u>.

### DEPUTY MANAGER | HCL TECHNOLOGIES, NOIDA, INDIA | FEB 2017 - JAN 2018

- I joined the HCL machine learning division (Noida) when this was a 3 members team. In the span of one year, we conducted 4 successful POCs and grew the team to a 16 members team.
- As a deputy manager my responsibilities were to handle the client interaction, project scoping, find the place where machine learning solutions can be pitched (to integrated with existing workflows) within and outside the organization.
- Helped my team to setup the machine learning GPU infrastructure, sketching project roadmaps, resource allocation
  and tracking. Further motivating team to follow the software engineering best practices such as maintaining git,
  hygiene of code (following the coding standards), etc.

### ML ENGINEER | ECLERX SERVICES LIMITED, MUMBAI, INDIA | NOV 2015 - FEB 2017

eClerx is an Indian IT consulting and outsourcing multinational company. I worked there as a full stack developer
and my job was to design and develop NLP, ML solutions. We used image pre-processing to improve OCR accuracy,
further to integrate these solutions with RPA system.

### Education

PH.D | HUMAN-ROBOT INTERACTION | DEC 2016 | IIIT, ALLAHABAD, INDIA

M.TECH | INFORMATION SECURITY | JUNE 2011 | KIIT UNIVERSITY, BHUBANESHWAR, INDIA

M.SC | INFORMATION TECHNOLOGYU | JUNE 2009 | KUMAUN UNIVERSITY, ALMORA, INDIA

B.SC | MATHEMATICS | JUNE 2007 | KUMAUN UNIVERSITY, ALMORA, INDIA

### **Skills & Abilities**

- Machine Learning
- Computer vision
- Natural language processing
- Certified scrum master
- Genetic Algorithms, Fuzzy Systems
- Human-Robot Interactions (Nao, Pepper)

- Machine learning operations (MLOps)
- AWS, GCP, E2E cloud platforms
- Python, TensorFlow, Pytorch, MySQL
- Git, CI/CD, Dockers, Micro Services (REST), JIRA
- IOT ESP32, MQTT, Jetson Nano, Raspberry, NXP

### Certifications

- Machine Learning Operations (MLOps)
   Coursera Deeplearnining.ai
   Focus Areas ML Workflows, TFX, Model Deployments
   and Tracking for Production
   May 3, 2022
- TensorFlow 2 for Deep Learning
   Coursera Imperial College London
   Focus Areas TensorFlow 2 APIs, Customized Model
   Training, Probabilistic Deep Learning
   Jul 9, 2023
- Machine Learning and Soft Computing Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India
   Focus Areas – Artificial Neural Network, Computer Vision and Genetic Algorithms
   Dec 20, 2012
- Building Cloud Computing Solutions at Scale Coursera – Duke University
   Focus Areas – Containers, Cloud APIs, DevOps, AWS an Azure
   Nov 6, 2023
- Scrum Master Certification Specialization
   Coursera Learn Quest
   Focus Areas Agile Methodology and Product
   Management
   Feb 17, 2023

### **Achievements**

- SOPHIA A H2020 EU PROJECT
   Secured a three years post-doctoral position on deep learning perception for human-robot collaboration at LIRMM Montpellier.
- POST-DOCTORAL FUNDING FROM KEMPHE FOUNDATIONS, SWEDEN
   Received 2 years of research funding to pursue my postdoctoral work in Human-Robot Interaction at Umea University, Sweden.
- 1ST POSITION IN M.SC
   Secured first position in M.Sc for consecutive 2 years at university level.
- MARIE SKŁODOWSKA CURIE ACTIONS (MSCA) 2020
   Applied for the MSCA post-doctoral funding in association with Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Spain and received 85% marks.
- MHRD, INDIA PH.D FELLOWSHIP
   Received 2 years of junior research and 2 years of senior research funding from MHRD for the Ph.D program under robotics and AI lab, IIIT Allahabad.

# **Projects**

#### **SMART VISION - BRANE ENTERPRISES**

We created a smart eyewear prototype equipped with an integrated camera to aid visually impaired individuals. Our in-house fabrication of the PCB board enables essential functionalities like Bluetooth connectivity, USB charging, and live streaming to an Android device. Additionally, we developed a companion app providing features such as object detection, scene analysis, navigation assistance, and person counting. My role involved collaborating with the team to develop and integrate deep learning solutions into the app. Together, we successfully implemented multiple models for object detection, image/dense captioning, currency recognition, OCR, and more.

Techniques Used: Faster-RCNN, MobileNetV2, CNN+LSTM, YOLO

### **INCREMENTAL FACE LEARNING - BRANE ENTERPRISES**

We developed an Android application for conducting face recognition using transfer learning techniques. We utilized the FaceNet model as the backbone network and added a classification layer for face classification. One challenge with neural networks is catastrophic forgetting, where training the entire network (excluding the backbone) on N+1 classes can lead to performance issues. To address this, we adopted an incremental learning approach that helps to train and deploy the model in 30 seconds reducing the onboarding time.

Techniques Used: Transfer Learning, FaceNet, Incremental Learning

### **ACTION RECOGNITION - MONTPELLIER UNIVERSITY**

Given one second long measure of the human's motion, the system can determine human action. The originality lies in the use of joint angles, instead of cartesian coordinates. This design choice makes the framework sensor agnostic and invariant to affine transformations and to anthropometric differences. On AnDy dataset, we outperform the state of art classifier. Furthermore, we show that our system is effective with limited training data, that it is subject independent, and that it is compatible with robotic real time constraints. In terms of methodology, the system is an original synergy of two antithetical schools of thought: model based and data-based algorithms. Indeed, it is the cascade of an inverse kinematics estimator compliant with the International Society of Biomechanics recommendations, followed by a deep learning architecture based on Bidirectional Long Short Term Memory.

Techniques Used: Transfer Learning, FaceNet, Incremental Learning

#### VISUAL GROUNDING - UMEA UNIVERSITY

For robots to engage with humans in real-world situations or with objects, they must develop a mental representation ("state of mind") that a) reflects the robots' perception and b) ideally aligns with human comprehension and ideas. Using table-top scenarios as an example, we propose a framework for generating a robot's "state of mind" by

identifying the objects on the table along with their characteristics (color, shape, texture) and spatial relationships to one another. The robot's view of the scene is depicted in a dynamic graph where object attributes are translated into fuzzy linguistic variables that correspond to human spatial concepts. This endeavor involves creating these graph representations through a combination of low-level neural network-based feature recognition and a high-level fuzzy inference system.

Techniques Used: Fuzzy Inference System, Mask-RCNN, CNN, Local Binary pattern (LBP), Multi-Layer Perceptron

### INTELLIGENT DOCUMENT PROCESSING - HCL TECHNOLOGIES

When dealing with scanned invoices from various vendors, our task involved extracting key information like invoice number, invoice date, vendor name, vendor address, total amount, and more. Our process begins with using Tesseract for OCR to digitize the invoices, followed by employing machine learning techniques to extract this data. We converted each word into a vector space and then classified it into its corresponding class, with each entity treated as a separate class. As OCR can introduce errors in the extracted values, we utilized domain ontology for error correction purposes. Techniques Used: Feature engineering, Multiclass classification, error correction.

### **Talks and Presentations**

- Title: An empirical review of calibration techniques for the Pepper humanoid robot's RGB and depth camera. Venue: Intelligent systems and application, 5th Sep 2019, London, England.
  - Occasion: Presented conference paper in IntelliSys 2019.
- Fusion of gesture and speech for increased accuracy in human robot interaction.
  - Venue: 25th International conference on methods and models in automation and robotics, 24th Aug 2019, Międzyzdroje, Poland.
  - Occasion: Presented conference paper in MMAR 2019.
- Conflict Detection and Resolution in Table Top Scenarios for Human-Robot Interaction.
  - Venue: Computing science department, Umea University, 18th Jun, 2019, Umea, Sweden.
  - Occasion: Poster presentation in 31st Swedish AI Society Workshop.
- Deep learning and its applications.
  - $\label{thm:continuous} \mbox{Venue: UFBI department, Umea University, $15^{th}$ Jun 2018, Umea, Sweden.}$
  - Occasion: Invited as a speaker at Umea center for Functional Brain Imaging (UFBI) day.
- Robotic Vision: Object Localization and Recognition
  - Venue: Department of Information Technology, NIT Raipur, 30th Dec, 2017, NIT Raipur, India.
  - Occasion: Guest Speaker in Computational Intelligence & Cloud Computing (CICC-2017) workshop.
- Artificial Intelligence and the Future of Robotics.
  - $\label{thm:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer:computer$
  - Occasion: Guest Speaker at ACM student chapter inauguration.
- Sketch drawing by NAO humanoid robot.
  - Venue: TENCON a premier international technical conference of IEEE Region 10, 1st Nov, 2015, Macau, China. Occasion: Presented conference paper in TENCON 2015.

# **Selected Publications [ Journals and Conferences]**

### **JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS**

- Singh, A. K., Baranwal, N., Richter, K. F., Hellström, T., & Bensch, S. (2020). Verbal explanations by collaborating robot teams. Paladyn, Journal of Behavioral Robotics, 12(1), 47-57.
- Singh, A. K., Baranwal, N., & Nandi, G. C. (2019). A rough set based reasoning approach for criminal identification.
   International Journal of Machine Learning and Cybernetics, 10, 413-431.
- Baranwal, N., Nandi, G. C., & Singh, A. K. (2017). Real-Time Gesture–Based Communication Using Possibility Theory–Based Hidden Markov Model. Computational Intelligence, 33(4), 843-862.

- Baranwal, N., Singh, A. K., & Nandi, G. C. (2017). Development of a framework for human-robot interactions with Indian sign language using possibility theory. International Journal of Social Robotics, 9, 563-574.
- Singh, A. K., Baranwal, N., & Nandi, G. C. (2017). Development of a self reliant humanoid robot for sketch drawing.
   Multimedia Tools and Applications, 76, 18847-18870.
- Singh, A. K., & Nandi, G. C. (2016). NAO humanoid robot: Analysis of calibration techniques for robot sketch drawing.
   Robotics and Autonomous Systems, 79, 108-121.
- Singh, A. K., Joshi, P., & Nandi, G. C. (2014). Face liveness detection through face structure analysis. International Journal of Applied Pattern Recognition, 1(4), 338-360.

### **CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS**

- Singh, A. K., Adjel, M., Bonnet, V., Passama, R., & Cherubini, A. (2022, November). A framework for recognizing industrial actions via joint angles. In 2022 IEEE-RAS 21st International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids) (pp. 210-216). IEEE.
- Kumar Singh, A., Baranwal, N., & Richter, K. F. (2020). A fuzzy inference system for a visually grounded robot state of mind. In ECAI 2020 (pp. 2402-2409). IOS Press.
- Singh, A. K., Baranwal, N., & Richter, K. F. (2020). An empirical review of calibration techniques for the pepper humanoid robot's RGB and depth camera. In Intelligent Systems and Applications: Proceedings of the 2019 Intelligent Systems Conference (IntelliSys) Volume 2 (pp. 1026-1038). Springer International Publishing.
- Singh, A. K., Chakraborty, P., & Nandi, G. C. (2015, November). Sketch drawing by nao humanoid robot. In TENCON 2015-2015 IEEE Region 10 Conference (pp. 1-6). IEEE.
- Singh, A. K., Kumar, A., Nandi, G. C., & Chakroborty, P. (2014, July). Expression invariant fragmented face recognition. In 2014 International Conference on Signal Propagation and Computer Technology (ICSPCT 2014) (pp. 184-189). IEEE.
- Singh, A. K., & Nandi, G. C. (2012, October). Face recognition using facial symmetry. In Proceedings of the second international conference on computational science, engineering and information technology (pp. 550-554).

Please find the complete list of publication at my Google Scholar Profile.

### **Online Presence**

Github: https://github.com/dravinash

<u>LinkedIn</u>: https://fr.linkedin.com/in/dr-avinash-kumar-singh-2a570a31 <u>Google Scholar</u>: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=eH9aB9kAAAAJ